<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Daniele Grattarola</title>
    <description>A blog about AI, recommender systems, and other interesting stuff.</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="nathanrooy.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 08:55:39 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 08:55:39 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.4.3</generator>
      
    
    <item>
        <title>Overthinking Japan</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/2017-10-31/shinjuku.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Piss Alley in Shinjuku, Tokyo (ph. Daniele Grattarola)&quot; class=&quot;full-width&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went to Japan with the expectation of finding a culture perfectly balanced 
between the immovable certainty of the past and the unforgiving, unstoppable
forward pull of the future. These are, after all, the two forces that I find myself subject to every day of my life: a hard, consolidated core of ground beliefs and values (like family, loyalty, tradition), and a constant attraction towards the bleeding edge, the unknown, the new.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t hide, however, that there are other reasons for which this unique country exercises a heavy charisma over me, reasons that I think can be easily shared by many other people of my generation.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For one, childhood. I grew up with a substantial percentage of my entertainment, and by extension the center of mass around which my happiness gravitated (read: the games that I played as a kid), coming from Japan.&lt;br /&gt;
Cartoons, comic books, games, video games: Japanese, or Japanese representations of the western world. 
It’s not a mystery that in times of uncertainty, or difficulty, we turn to the past to seek happiness, and I think that even for someone with a healthy and (semi) successful life there are factors for which this mechanism could become relevant. The constant competition of your peers, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ribbonfarm.com/2017/08/17/the-premium-mediocre-life-of-maya-millenial/&quot;&gt;premium mediocrity&lt;/a&gt; of our millenial lives, the melting economic glacier: all potential reasons for which one could want to look back, rather than ahead. 
This does not mean that I consciously weighted this aspect when planning my trip, but it could explain a bias when I spun the globe and pointed to the destination for a self-searching, once-in-a-lifetime solo travel after graduation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/2017-10-31/osaka.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Osaka seen from the Tsutenkaku tower (ph. Daniele Grattarola)&quot; class=&quot;full-width&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And another important component of this bias is, unsurprisingly, the Internet. 
I don’t mean the internet of social media, forums, “AI” journalism, and porn. I mean the Internet as an entity, with a capital “I”. The omnipotent and omniscient God of the Internet Kvlt, the powerful, unaccessible aesthetical phenomenon at the center of Vaporwave, the enabling technology of cyberpunk, the tyrant freedom and freeing tyranny of our lives. It’s that thing that you can’t explain to your parents when they ask you why memes are a thing.&lt;br /&gt;
The blast of the Internet was heavily fueled by Japanese culture and aesthetics, and we, as a collective, elected Japan as the physical embodiment of our intangible universe of information.&lt;br /&gt;
There are interesting and complex aspects to this, because while Japan was being brought forth as the de facto land of the Internet, Japanese millenials were diving deeper and deeper into the Internet culture, tumbling in a downward (or upward) spiral until the country became the conceptual caricature of itself, an entity that doesn’t need to stress its characteristics in order to make them evident, because it already managed to erase the barrier between reality and its representation. If you think about it, this is the same exact phenomenon that characterizes the Internet (again, capital “I”), where information transcends the real world and becomes meta-information. 
And I find in this meta-information, in the post-post-post-ironic memes, in monospaced fonts, classic statues over pink backgrounds, 80’s aesthetics, 8-bit music, and glitch art the most fascinating cultural movement of our time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given these (at least two) sources of bias in my choice, I booked a flight and headed to Japan.&lt;br /&gt;
As expected, it was exactly what I thought it would be. But it was even more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When walking alone in the forests, the firework-like cities, or the wooden temples from which you could see all the way down to your Self, I was humming the mono themes from Pokemon Gold because that’s where my mind would go more often than not. I found myself spending six hours in Akihabara mesmerized by the otaku culture even if I don’t even watch anime anymore (if I ever did at all). I almost cried at the neon covered buildings because there I realized that cyberpunk aesthetic is real, and that I was there to witness it. The barrier between reality and its representation in my mind shattered, as if by being there I became part of the meta-universe myself.&lt;br /&gt;
A big part of what enabled this to happen is the almost constant solitude in which I lived for 15 days, with a linguistic barrier there to isolate me even from the passive communication around me and facilitating the deconstruction of reality which was going on in my mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/2017-10-31/buddha.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Golden Buddha in Shitenno-ji temple, Osaka (ph. Daniele Grattarola)&quot; class=&quot;full-width&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there was the introspection, because you can’t help but think about your existence when you find yourself staring at a ten meter golden Buddha who, in turn, stares back at you with a mystical power so strong that the statue itself seems to be alive. And in those moments, armed with a few simple spiritual axioms that I picked up over the years, I could make sense of religion as a whole, not by embracing it, but by tearing it apart and understanding the mechanism underneath, with the same level of comprehension that you would get by opening up a clock and seeing the cogs, rather than simply using it to read the time (or, for me, seeing other people using it, as luckily I never felt the need of an outside force to explain my unknowns).&lt;br /&gt;
By looking past the religious wall, I could then easily navigate philosophy (again, armed of a few authors that I have in my cultural baggage) and try to make sense of existence, or what derives thereof (&lt;a href=&quot;http://exsubstantia.com/about&quot;&gt;ex substantia&lt;/a&gt;), because only in those specific situations the Search could yield results.&lt;br /&gt;
This last level is what, for me, completed the unification, what finally removed the Veil of Maya and made me experience the metaphysical through the senses, and in turn explained the aristotelian Act by deconstructing the Potency, by stepping into Plato’s cave and forcing the true concepts to come out to the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, what this trip meant for me was a step forward to a view of existence in which all barriers between the real and the conceptualized are pointless, where either can be used to convey meaning to one’s life and where substance (i.e. the true essence of things) can be found in either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides overthinking, however, getting to know a different culture was amazing, the food was mind-blowing, I met amazing people, and learning Japanese is being lots of fun. I feel like I’m now ready to start a new adventure, like this trip was the perfect full stop to my first chapter and the start of a new one, in which I will test myself in the international arena of research and maybe, hopefully, leave a trace in the advances of humanity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I warmly suggest you to check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://insidekyoto.com&quot;&gt;Inside Kyoto&lt;/a&gt; to get around Japan, it made the whole trip a lot more enjoyable for me.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        
        <link>/posts/2017-10-31/overthinking-japan.html</link>
          
        
            <category>travel</category>
        
            <category>philosophy</category>
        
          
        
            <category>posts</category>
        
          
      </item>
    
    <item>
        <title>The Fermi Paradox of Superintelligence</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/2017-09-25/seti.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Allen Telescope Array (Public domain)&quot; class=&quot;full-width&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attirbuted to Enrico Fermi as a back-of-the-envelope astrobiological philosphy 
exercise, Fermi’s paradox is a simply put question: &lt;em&gt;where is everybody?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In other words, if life is a truly common phenomenon in the universe, then
the probability of a civilization solving the problem of interstellar travel
should be pretty high, and the effects of such a civilization on the galaxy 
should be extremely evident to an observer (think entire stars being instantly 
harvested for power).&lt;br /&gt;
However, the SETI remains unsuccessful, hence where is everyone? 
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://scholar.google.it/scholar?q=fermi+paradox&quot;&gt;A quick search on Scholar&lt;/a&gt;
will give you literally thousands of reasons not to panic (or maybe do the
opposite, depending on how much you like aliens), and provide you with many
logical reasons why the presence of ETI could go unnoticed, leaving us in our
quiet and lonely neighborhood.&lt;br /&gt;
Having sorted that out, we can safely go back to our Twitter feeds to discuss
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dog_rates/status/775410014383026176&quot;&gt;serious business&lt;/a&gt; 
and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2017/aug/14/elon-musk-ai-vastly-more-risky-north-korea&quot;&gt;Elon Musk’s latest views on AI&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
We can also go back to our comfy evening reads, which in my case mean Hofstader’s
&lt;em&gt;GEB&lt;/em&gt; (for the sixth time or so) and Nick Bostrom’s &lt;em&gt;Superintelligence&lt;/em&gt;, 
while listening to the sound of the falling rain.
And then, when the words are stirring inside your head, and the rain has
flushed the world clean, and the only sound you can hear is the quiet whir
of the GPU fan, while it’s training that 10-layer net that you’ve been recently
working on; only then, you might find yourself asking the question: &lt;em&gt;where the hell is superintelligence?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a reasonable question, isn’t it? Just look at all the informed opinions 
of the better, wiser people than me that I cited above on the subject. 
They may disagree on its nature, but no one (&lt;em&gt;no one&lt;/em&gt;) disagrees that AGI will 
have an almost infinite growth rate.&lt;br /&gt;
Go back to the second sentence of this post, and replace “interstellar travel”
with “artificial intelligence” to have an idea of what that may look like. 
And we’re not talking of a simple Kardashev scale boost; a superintelligence would
be well aware of its physical limitations, so we would likely be looking at an
end-of-the-galaxy scenario, with all available matter being converted to 
computing infrastructure, &lt;em&gt;à la&lt;/em&gt; Charles Stross.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A phenomenon so powerful that its mere exisistence would change the scale of 
reference for every other phenomena in the universe, something so good at self
imporving that it would only be limited by physical laws.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the probability of life in the universe is high, then so is the probability
of a civilization developing a superintelligence, with all its extremely evident
effects.&lt;br /&gt;
So where is it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, I only talked about a catastrophic scenario following the creation of a
superintelligence, but we have to consider the postive and neutral outcomes, 
before denying the existence of a super AI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the effects of a superintelligence on its universe were not so devastating, 
if we look at the brightest end of the spectrum of possibility, think about the 
advances that such an entity would bring to its creators. All the technologically
motivated solutions to the Fermi paradox, at that point, would be null, leaving
us with a whole lot less formal analysis, and a whole lot more speculation on
alien sociology and superintelligent motives.&lt;br /&gt;
What reason could a civilization with a superintelligence in its toolbox have 
to not reach out of its planet?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, we couldn’t still exclude a catastrophic end of the galaxy, if the 
computational necessities of the AI required it to favor an absolute good
(its existence) to a relative one (our existence).
Therefore, if we allow for a truly &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; superintelligence to exist somewhere
in the universe right now, we have to imagine natural, moral, or logical 
impediments that prevent it from communicating outwards and spreading infinite 
progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From another perspective, even if talking about &lt;em&gt;likelihood&lt;/em&gt; in this context 
is a serious gnoseological gamble, it seems that the neutral scenarios would 
likely be the less noticeable: superintelligence is there, but it has no drive 
to manifest itself.&lt;br /&gt;
That could either be for a lack of necessity (it wouldn’t need energy, or matter, 
or information), or a lack of advantage (it wouldn’t want to reveal its presence
to avoid danger, or to avoid pointless expenses of limited resources), and it 
would be a fairly easy and rational explanation to the superintelligence paradox.&lt;br /&gt;
A system in such a perfect equilibrium would probably exist in a super-state, 
free from the unforgiving grip of entropy and eternally undetected (short of
using another superintelligence, at which point the paradox would already be
solved).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stop here with the examples, because it’s out of my capabilities to summarize
all possible scenarios, especially when we consider that the Fermi paradox has 
inspired fifty years of debate. 
And if we think about this debate, we see that it extends back in the ages, 
that “alien civilization”, “AI”, or “God” have been used interchangeably without
 changing the essence of the discourse: why, if &lt;em&gt;they&lt;/em&gt; exist, are they not 
 manifest?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As hard as we try to rationalize this question, we perfectly know that there
are only two possible outcomes, that we are looking for a black swan that we will
either find, or keep looking for. At the same time, we’ve learned very well 
how to coexist with this uncertainty, because we only need the possibility of a
forced ignorance, in order to accept an ignorance undesired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so, as men of rational intellects we can be crushed by the lack of knowledge, 
or be incessantly driven by it, knowing that every second spent in the search 
is a second that could have only be wasted otherwise. And those who are crushed, 
may turn to faith, and find peace in knowing that their happiness resides with 
the black swan, where it can’t be touched by mortal sight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, while telling us a lot about human condition, this thought leaves
us back in our quiet neighborhood of probable but unverifiable truths.&lt;br /&gt;
However, when considering the practically null amout of time that constitutes our
lives, a question may come to one’s mind: is it closer to human nature to 
think of a God, or to seek one out?&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        
        <link>/posts/2017-09-25/fermi-paradox-ai.html</link>
          
        
            <category>AI</category>
        
          
        
            <category>posts</category>
        
          
      </item>
    
    <item>
        <title>New Blog</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/header/oz.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Australian Outback (ph. Daniele Grattarola)&quot; class=&quot;full-width&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog is an updated version of my old edgy, teenage-years blog at &lt;a href=&quot;http://exsubstantia.com&quot;&gt;exsubstantia.com&lt;/a&gt;.
I kept a somewhat similar style because I like the way Exsubstantia looks, but I hope that the difference in content
will speak for itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will use this blog to talk mostly about two things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;interesting concepts that I come across when working on my research and projects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;interesting stuff that I come across when traveling around&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;but I’ll try to keep it varied, and also talk about other interesting things. 
I will try to include code whenever necessary, but for more complex projects you can check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/danielegrattarola&quot;&gt;my Github&lt;/a&gt;.
You can also find me on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/riceasphait&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/riceasphait/&quot;&gt;Instagram&lt;/a&gt; as @riceasphait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        
        <link>/posts/2017-09-19/new-blog.html</link>
          
        
            <category>update</category>
        
          
        
            <category>posts</category>
        
          
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
